this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
sea radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
[Music]
hello SC radio listeners I'm po Chen
head of engineering at qliksen we're a
cloud Communications company if you're
considering building text messaging into
your projects you'll like using our SMS
API tens of thousands of Engineers
around the world do plus for SE radio
listeners there's 50 of free credit to
try Clicks in just visit qliksen.com SC
radio that's quicksand.com SE radio now
enjoy the podcast
hello and welcome to software
engineering radio today we are going to
talk about the protocols of the internet
I've got the great pleasure of
introducing Varun Singh Varun is the
Chief Products and Technology officer at
Daily Dot Co bringing over two decades
of expertise in Video Communications
he previously co-founded and served as
the CEO of callstats.io a leading
performance monitoring service for
webrtc Varun has made significant
contributions to the field co-authoring
12 ietf and w3c specifications earning
several patents in real-time
Communications and receiving special
recognition from the ACM multimedia for
his PhD thesis which improved web
browser call Quality he earned his PhD
in multimedia networks and the Telecom
from alto University Helsinki in Finland
welcome to the show Varun is there
anything that I missed in your
introduction that you would like to add
no thank you for having me it's a
pleasure talking to you and to reflect
on the last 30 years of the internet so
I'm really happy to be here yeah it is
an interesting topic so let's just dive
right into it I think one of the first
topics that we wanted to talk about was
this concept of protocol lossification
so what is protocol ossification so
protocol ossification means the loss of
flexibility in evolving a protocol and
in this case you're talking about a
suite of protocols like the tcpip in
HTTP although I would say that without
protocol lossification we would not have
achieved the success that we did in the
intervening years so I can talk a little
bit about history and like why like in
retrospect we call it ossification but
while it was happening we didn't
consider it as an ossification sure but
before we get into that maybe some
examples of protocols that have
experienced ossification and why this is
such a concern it's a good question so
if you think about like when we talk
about networking or the internet we a
lot of times talk about the OSI model
which is like the seven layers right and
if you think about that's existed for
almost 50 years now from since the 60s
70s since arpanet and then we had TCP IP
the first we had IP then we had TCP and
such and in the 90s actually in the
beginning of the 90s when the web came
around in 94 which is like the 30th
Anniversary Justice this year actually
this month yeah I know so if you think
about like when the web came around
there were so many methods of
communicating on the internet and for
the web to win we needed ossification to
happen in retrospect ossification so
what happened was you we had IP ipv4
specifically ipv4 addresses that had to
win so once ip1 then the thing on top of
it was TCP TCP won the game against the
other protocols and then HTTP which was
on top of TCP like proliferated internet
right so today if you think about
anything like we basically everything is
a web service and everything that was
not aware like everything that we have
today was also not a web service email
for example like we don't use any of the
SMTP or any of those protocols today
like we just use the web like you know
we go to website Gmail or whatever
provider you have open a web browser and
the the server side is actually still
communicate in SMTP but like for us as
users we have stopped using that's HTTP
one in some sense so ossification is
like the TCP IP HTTP that Trio got
ossified and everything is built on top
of that so everything that is built on
that HTTP TCP IP Foundation has to
follow all the constraints of that
product all these three protocols now if
right so if we start to build something
new which needs to expand like the way
HTTP or TCP or IP needs to behave then
you're constrained you can't actually do
that and one good example of that was in
or before 2010 like when Web 2.0 started
that movement Google realized that
like Google was really concerned about
like page load times they were very very
crazy about it and that was like one of
the metrics which drove the idea that we
had ossified because until 2008 like
people kind of knew that we had ossified
but no one actually cared about it it's
just that when we started to focus on
page load time specifically Google they
realized that they couldn't actually
push it Beyond a certain point because
they were constrained by HTTP in its
current format and then like TCP in
below that and if you wanted to reduce
the page load times then we had to like
kind of make some more changes on those
protocols
right now and just to kind of explore
that idea a little bit further also
right so if it let's take the Google
example right so if you're thinking as a
Google engineer you have the Google web
servers and the Google infrastructure
that was already state of the art and
then around 2010 they came up with the
idea okay let's build our own browser
right so now you have the other end of
the thing which is basically Chrome and
theoretically you could build in
whatever protocol or whatever you wanted
in into Chrome but they still were
having this fundamental problem and
that's mainly because of the pieces in
between so maybe you could talk about a
little bit about why that is kind of I
think the secret reason why this
ossification can happen that's actually
a good observation so like if you think
about the networks and like one thing
that you're learning like networking 101
is like the end-to-end principle and
when you talk about the end-to-end
principle the end-to-end principle
basically says that the two end hosts
should decide what they want to do they
should have full flexibility and once
they agree on something they should be
able to do it and that's what you asked
like you I said like you know Google got
Chrome and Chrome gave them a big
advantage of owning one side the client
side of the infrastructure and they're
on the the server side of the
infrastructure themselves so one big
thing is the middle boxes but more like
another thing to consider is that the
TCP protocol itself is actually
implemented in the kernel of the
in-house
so right so you have the browser which
has HTTP and all these new things it has
the TCP stack which is implemented in
the kernel and TCP is also a little bit
quirky like it kind of depends on which
side you're the sender of the receiver
when we talk about where most of the
data is actually coming from the server
side so there's a little bit more
flexibility on the on the server side to
actually say oh you know I want to send
a lot of data like can I send you a lot
of data and the client can say like yeah
send me all the date like send me more
data so there's some complexity there
that they had to go around but more
importantly like the middle boxes so one
of the biggest constraints like why we
have only TCP and UDP we have also other
parallel protocols satp and such but
because the
we all are connected to an ISP the isps
are connected to something and then they
are connected to the cloud right
typically like Amazon's not directly
connected to there are all these layers
of players in between you and like
Netflix or un Google and they all have
infrastructure
and initially because of security
reasons and malicious traffic a lot of
isps actually block a lot of the traffic
right so like they're like first they
call themselves The bastions of security
because they're like the first thing
that can either Ingress or egress from
inside the network they can stop what
goes outside and whatever's coming from
outside can stop inside and they decided
in their Infinite Wisdom that they would
only allow TCP to go on out because most
of the traffic was on HTTP anyway right
so like basically you stop that and if
you remember like in the early 2000s
there were like attacks on SMTP because
a lot of like Linux devices and like
other devices ran like SMTP servers
locally on your on your device you
didn't even realize and then we had some
problems and you could run your own SMTP
server and spoof anybody's email and all
that right and people were trying to get
access through like Port 53 for you know
whatever ports were open and if there
was like an exploit on like a zero to
exploit on some software that was like
no one is using but it's still running
because it came with whatever you got
like you know whatever operating system
basically the ISP is blocked almost
everything so you could not start adding
a new protocol on top of Ip which
totally allows like there is like a
Infinite Space of protocols that you can
add on top of and there are like satp
and dccp and like there's so many
protocols there but they can never
Traverse
like they may run in your home network
but they would never go outside of your
home network until like onto the web for
example right so the middle boxes were
of course a bit of a problem because
they were basically filtering the
traffic
and Google could not talk to all the
isps in the world and the so there was
no like you know economic action like
you know you say oh capitalism would win
in this case but no like capitalism
cannot like there are none of those two
things like the people who want the
service and people who are providing the
service could not make this you know
middle boxers
quickly enough right so that was one of
the main challenges and also the
opportunity because it was a standard
Network you could you could put anything
on it and everybody spoke HTTP TCP we
had this Cambrian explosion that became
the internet I guess the next thing to
talk about would be then okay so we have
TCP and then we have HTTP on top of it
HTTP did evolve right so maybe you can
start from what is the evolution of HTTP
we have now I think the recent one is
HTTP 3 but we had various versions of
HTTP before that can you kind of talk
about how that happened and you know
what were some of the features that each
one of the new versions came up with
it's important to like reflect on like
how Evolution happens so so when we had
HTTP 1.0 it was just like the first
attempt of getting text across the
internet yeah this was like 1996 or
something 94 it was public release so
that's why 30 years yeah yeah all right
93 94. it was I think already in CERN
since 1991 I think or even before so it
had evolved as part of like Sun's need
for like sharing data for for the
physics experiments that they were doing
across universities and their network of
of servers and then it proliferated
outside of that and when it proliferated
initially like I think the simplest
thing to say is like it was very simple
it was text based protocol right and was
like yeah it was mainly for sharing
papers between scientists it was never
meant to be a protocol for for business
yeah you didn't want to send a PDF
across the net so like basically it was
you have text you have some images which
is what makes up most of the scientific
papers and you know some level of
interactivity so you could like have a t
talk table of content you could jump
between so you're hyperlinking and
because you didn't need a flat file so
you could organize data right like in in
some more meaningful way so you could
have like an Abridged version and then
you know you could basically delve
deeper so you had HTTP then 1.0 and I
think we didn't come up with H1 h2h3
this nomenclature until HTTP 2 because
everyone before that just called it HTTP
and then 1.1 came because like 1.1 was a
big change because before that HTTP was
just considered one protocol and then
HTTP became like two parts like one was
the syntax and the other thing was
semantics and syntax was basically the
network and the format and what goes
over the wire and all that stuff and the
semantics were basically like headers
response codes like what's actually a
method so like get put all that got
separated so one big game like the
semantics and then syntax so you could
like have more like you could change
methods you could add more methods you
could add more response codes you could
send HTTP 1.1 the biggest thing that I
remember was keeper lives like that like
that came through and then you know like
this was around so your timeline when
you said you know 96 97 that was like
the Netscape versus the browser Wars so
that was the time when it could be 1.1
km it basically almost all the Amazon
the Googles like they're all emerged in
that period of time no yeah super
successful and then you go 10 years
forward to like 2005 2008 2009 this kind
of period where web2. okay
and Web 2.0 and especially Google we
talked about like they were very
concerned about page load time so they
started to push and if you think about
page load time like you know you're just
sending a piece of a page and it could
be a blank page right and if you just
send a blank page and if you just look
at like the performance of HTTP with
HTTP 1.1 HTTP 2 it should be just on a
blank page and see like how how quickly
it gets across right and then you can
add more semantics on top of it and you
say so HTTP 1.1 and HTTP 2 like the big
thing was that they wanted to and
actually before HTTP 2 there were like
some experiments by Google called speedy
and how speedy what was that it was
trying to be 1.1 and they tried to
change like I said before and you also
remark that they had Chrome the browser
so they could change a bunch of things
inside their browser that could be much
faster you know like they had their own
V8 engine and all that stuff to like
basically accelerate anything at the
ends like but also the servers were
sending bulk data so if they could just
send more data and somehow like change
the congestion control algorithm on
their side to be more aggressive they
could so they started to tweak a lot of
things which you know if the client was
still using an archaic like kernel TCP
they could still try to like optimize
from the server side what to do but they
realized that one thing that they needed
to do was increase the initial window
from like the initial window of a TCP
like when you don't know anything about
anything you send like an initial window
of two packets so like basically if you
have to send something you either send
one packet you know that you can start
with one and then like then increase
then send two packets and see increases
yeah so like the most simplest algorithm
is aimd adaptive increase
multiplicative disk decrease which means
that every time you get an Accu
basically add one more but you start
with initial Windows 2 so you start with
two segments
after a lot of call like cajoling we
increased it to four they wanted it to
be seven right so like basically you
could send four packets right at the
front so they did that but that would
require like updates to you know a lot
of middle boxes and like the end points
and you know if you make a new kernel
today it would still take two three
years before it would become available
so Speedy started with the idea that
there would be some changes that will
happen there but one of the things that
were a big problem with HTTP 1.1 was
that you could not do pipelining or like
multiplexing or parallel Transmissions
so one of the things that we got in HTTP
one in HTTP 2 or H2 over H1 was that we
could paralyze communication so you
could like get chunks of multiple things
simultaneously in one connection yeah so
I think earlier before that I think they
were like having a browser squid opening
up multiple connections to one website
just so that they could load the server
first yeah and there was also like
basically browsers were told not to open
like more than two or three or so there
was also a limit on how many yeah yeah I
think it was six you couldn't go more
than five if you did zero to five and
after that basically you get throttle
exactly so HTTP 2 brought in this
concept of parallelization and adding
and kind of like streams into one
connection so that was in 2015 right
yeah so basically they presented the
idea in 2010 and I think in 2012 the
community was sufficiently agreed upon
that we need to do this and then two
three more years and then everything got
standardized yeah but already in 2014
2015 like YouTube was like probably the
first one which already moved that was
the biggest experiment and I think
already in 2012-13 they were already on
Speedy for several years in H2 a variant
of H2 right at Google and then when 2015
this like said it was done it was
already faced by Google Netflix a bunch
of them I think in even my startup call
stats we started we moved to H2 in 2017
2016 so like soon after as a startup it
takes a little bit more time because you
personally you need validation from the
market and you need a tool chain
available so you can actually be ahead
of the curve so obviously this was an
innovation over HTTP and the HTTP 2 came
around and it was 2017. and if you look
at the difference between HTTP which
came out like you said in 93 and then
HTTP 2 came out in 2015 which is kind of
almost like 20 years right and now
immediately almost it seems very fast
that HTTP 3 came out so what was the
main problem or what was the challenge
with HTTP 2 that you know kind of pushed
them to say hey no we need to kind of
solve this even better or this is not
not enough so the Speedy proposal made a
lot of changes or required a lot of
changes and not everything that Speedy
wanted was done mainly because we were
still stuck on TCP right so like the
changes they wanted to make to TCP were
not like really granted and what we
realized was that we can't make changes
to TCP because and even if we did make
changes to TCP you would still have to
go to BSD you would have to go to the
next year I would have to go to like so
many like Microsoft like people who own
the operating systems Android like you
need a lot of people to like agree on
making those changes to happen and one
of the things that was in H2 which we
kind of started was the head of light
blocking in HTTP so you talked about
streams right but like one of the things
that people noticed with streams was
that you couldn't actually make the
servers go faster because there were
still like head of line blocking
happening at the at the TCP layer below
could you explain a little bit about
that because as I understand it head of
line blocking is not entirely an HTTP
problem it's actually a TCP problem
right it's because TCP is kind of
sequenced so maybe can we go into a
little bit of why this is kind of right
so like head of line blocking means that
if you have packet number three waiting
to be sent and four is more important
you can't do anything about that because
three is still in the queue right and in
the issue GTP world it was resources so
you were thinking like the main thing
was that you could not download resource
two or three until Resource One was done
in parallel right and so like you had
these connections which you were like oh
use connection one to get Resource One
resource two but if all your like let's
say you had four connections and all of
them were stuck with resource one two
three four you're not blocked right like
you could not like at some point like a
user clicked something and say like
actually I want to cancel everything I
don't really care about these one two
three but what was this thing about
blocking right so why was it so easy to
block a TCP connection was it something
I mean because I remember back in the
day when I was running so TCP
essentially was one of those things that
used to guarantee it was a guaranteed
form of communication right so you could
basically if you send a piece of data
it's guaranteed to reach there and it
was reached there in a particular
sequence right so it was supposed to be
that okay if if you send three packets
packet one comes packet two one pack two
and packet three they will make sure
that it comes in that and they'll
present it to you in that sequence and I
think that's kind of one of the
weaknesses also right that's one of the
reasons why there is this ahead of line
blocking yeah so think of this like if
you were just sending a text file right
like if you're just sending a text file
basically it would start reading from
the front of the file and then just
basically all the lines would appear in
order now if something gets lost and you
if you got like let's say one line is
one packet for Simplicity for people
right like you have like 1500 lines and
you'll send 1500 packets one after the
other the simplest like forget TCP or
whatever like basically what you would
say like there are many ways to do this
you would send all the 1500 packets like
as fast the other side would tell you
like what got lost then you would do a
second pass and say like oh pack like
lines 4 15 16 17 18 21 22 got lost I
will send it you'll send them right at
the end
but until you got to the end you could
not present anything right exactly so
that is the head of line blocking so
even so you have like 90 of the file
with you in the server if for whatever
reason one line was missing
you actually would not actually see it
so what I explained like what the
simplest example I gave is like how FTP
servers worked initially like FTP
servers just sent like as fast as
possible reported like what was missing
you sent everything once they had
everything then you could see the file
so TCP or HTTP or whatever does it in a
slightly different way because if you
have like three lines of the file why
can't you show three lines of the file
right right but if you got line five
like you got three lines then you got
line five like line six
but you don't know what's in line four
line four is missing so it'll actually
stop at that point even though you have
lines five six seven it won't render
until it gets line four right and that's
the initial window that I was talking
about like before the initial window
will grow so like as the window grows
like there are more things in queue now
if you're more things in queue you're
kind of blocked like you have 17 18
and actually as a server you know that
you're sending 19 and you actually say
like maybe like line four is like I'm
still pending four but it's not needed
now like you know for whatever reason it
has some content yeah maybe it's like
one frame in a video one one pixel of a
frame right and it says like that's part
of a different resource that resources
probably under the like you've already
scrolled down further that you don't
care about something there right so the
HTTP 2 solved the resource head of line
blocking in some sense right so
resources could come out of order and be
yeah but even then within a resource if
you had header line blocking that was a
problem and increasingly in the modern
web now we've got really large resources
right you have one fire which is a video
it could be a podcast for example which
is several megabytes yeah and you like
streaming is its own other problem when
we can come to that there are other
transports to that that can help but
like yeah you're right like the
resources that are big or there are too
many resources right like if you think
about Twitter and like this feed that
you're getting each tweet could be its
own resource right and like you may have
scrolled past a certain resource so you
don't really need that resource anymore
but it's still in flight so yeah so it's
to solve that and in H3 what they made
the decision so firstly we've made the
decision that we don't want to use TCP
it's too slow like Innovation TCP is too
slow to like move forward and so this
work had already begun in 2000 I mean
even before 25 like we start working on
H3 we start working on quick immediately
like in 2014 2015 people started to talk
about like you know we left some things
behind in Speedy we need to innovate and
a couple of working groups started
inside the iitf one was the quick
working group and then the other one was
Taps transport services and their idea
was that we have like now a problem we
have classification we can't actually
innovate on like new protocols we can't
build a new protocol so the only
protocol now we have is UDP and if we
can innovate on UDP and you know we talk
a lot about UDP and networking
one-on-one as connection less so
basically you can move some of the
responsibility that you need that you
got from TCP outside of TCP into UDP and
you say like I'll build a layer on top
of UDP that will do that same work and
that would be great just in the interest
of kind of making sure that you know the
audience is caught up can you kind of
quickly give us a high level overview of
the TCP versus UDP what are the
differences and a little bit of history
about where was UDP around when TCP was
there or was earlier like I think it is
like a few years earlier was UDP so UDP
is what we call a connection less and
TCP is called connection oriented I
think for if you're a beginner it makes
a lot of sense but as you grow into the
world like that separation only means
that UDP comes with very few services so
if you're building on top of UDP
something you take responsibility to
build all the services on top of it
right and so TCP what it gives is like
it's a connection oriented so what does
it mean like it's got a handshake so it
like talks to the other side says like
it sets up the connection and says hey
we have a connection now established now
you can send data over this connection
right like so you have a four-way
handshake or a three-way hand check TCP
since enack like people talk about that
so you do that handshake and then you
say now we have a connection we can set
up like we can now if you you can do
that on UDP as well like you could
create your own handshake but you'd have
to build it yourself it's not part of
that basically
UDP is bare bonds even more Bare Bones
sentences right and it's actually quite
difficult to get something built on UDP
and pass like you know get an RFC
because there are so many people big who
look at it and because you're building
you're not using any of the services
that are already available on other
protocols then you have to resolve the
problems that are like solved problems
so a lot of people did not want to build
on top of
UDP for obvious reasons because like
they would always get into this problem
of solving solved problems right so when
we came to do quick it became very
obvious that the solved problems that we
had like that TCP offered were actually
now constraints becoming kind of like
hazardous that they were concerned and
you could not innovate Beyond like so
basically you had to resolve the sort
problems knowing what like the edge
cases were right and now the edge cases
were big enough that you would say like
we have to go solve this so when we get
into HTTP 3 and quick what was the
thinking around how to actually tackle
this ossification issue had there has
there been identified or is there a
strategy within quick that will prevent
this particular thing from happening
with your UDP and yeah actually that's
also a very good question it's a quick
has a versioning and you don't like
basically we think of version numbers
most of them have like two bits like if
you go down to the protocols and you say
like how many bits do I have like you
have like two four bits you have a lot
more bits right on quick to like so
basically there's a version of quick
that everyone agrees and that's let's
say version one that version of quick is
what everyone's using today but you
could come up with a new version of
quick and you know like firstly you
wouldn't probably need something like a
browser or like an electron app or like
whatever like today you have native apps
so you could actually have like your own
version of quick which would be slightly
different if it would be for you yeah
and if you own the server side like if
you own both sides you could have your
own and you don't have to like talk to
anyone right but you still have the
middleman problem don't you we still
have the wooden the middle boxes
basically also protect you or they'll
say okay really good question because
like one thing that we skipped over that
we talked about earlier like why it took
us like another 10 years from like
Speedy to H3 and why we had to do H2 was
we had to convince everyone in the world
that we had to allow of traffic over UDP
because like if you think of a lot of
networks like even some isps Drop Like
UDP you can't actually send UDP across
the internet partly it was webrtc which
we'll talk about in passing webrtc
emerged as a web real-time communication
it already required UDP and it fought
you know for many years to like like get
UDP across a lot of networks and even
today
UDP gets blocked like if you're a
hospital if you're a bank you're like
some kind of Enterprise environment it's
quite possible like UDP gets blocked and
then what you do is you go over Port 443
so you masquerade UDP as a TCP transport
and like you basically find the nearest
top that you can go to over TCP so there
are ad servers you connect over TCP put
your UDP packets over TCP funnel it
through that boundary and then the other
side it goes over the UDP and then on
the other side go back to UDP right and
quick is kind of built on this udpy idea
right so fundamentally the middle box is
basically
the ones that we've webrtc opened up for
us for H3 basically allow UDP and they
don't actually realize that this is not
webrtc this is that yeah and it's all
encrypted so it doesn't like basically
it is a UDP connection and now if your
YouTube stops because it's on H3 it can
fall back to H2 but I think with time
we'll realize that the performance of H3
is so much better like Netflix and all
these people will require like people
who have relationships with the isps
where they find this UDP is blocked
they'll push really hard to get it
unblocked right because they would say
like hey if let's say some geography in
the world is having poor performance of
YouTube or Netflix people will like
basically want better services and you
know we spend so much time today
absolutely more than video calls we
spend more time on HTTP related services
and if they are actually degraded
because they're on H2 instead of H3 like
let's say we are AR like you know
they're bigger things there coming that
will push the boundaries so so I think
the doors are open it just took us maybe
like five additional years because of
this right so yeah the doors opened and
I think you mentioned also one thing
that quick was encrypted so when you
think about HTTP we have this actually
in between layer so you have IP and then
you have the TLs protocol in between the
TLs layer for doing the securing and
then you have HTTP on top is it the same
thing with quick or is this UDP etls and
quick or is this something that quick
does better no I think the
TLs is part of quick like basically TLS
dtls TLS datagram TLS so the main thing
is that HTTP 1 1.1 did not mandate HTTP
TLS and I think until 2 2010 it was not
even very common to see https on the
internets like if unless you're on a
credit card site or something you would
see like this lock icon appear and
everyone was told to look for the like
lock icon and then there was a big
movement towards like TLS everywhere or
https everywhere and I think it is only
this year or last year they claimed that
100 of the web is now on you know 99.9
like never 100 because there will always
be one side where it doesn't do
something but you know we're at like
four or five nines now that everyone has
HTTP certificates and actually it's a
very good question because in 2010 if
you said like how would I get an HTTP
certificate it was very expensive it was
like 600 right and like most people who
wanted to run a website even if I cared
a lot about security if I was not doing
credit cards that there was no way that
I would like spend 600 for the
certificate so let's encrypt and there
was a limited certificate as well it was
not even a wildcat certificate yeah you
got like a very specific yeah and you
bought a wild card it was like even more
expensive like you know five thousand or
ten thousand or something because yeah
yeah it was crazy yes so yeah Okay cool
so we have encryption and quick as part
of the TLs thing and I I would imagine
that that kind of helps also because it
prevents the middle boxes from actually
seeing whether this is a quick it's a
losing game like the ciscos and the
junipers and everyone I think they
fought really hard to like protect their
business but it's also like if you think
about it took us 10 years to like kind
of navigate around them and now have you
know UDP and it took them 10 years and
if you think about what is the sunset
period of someone who bought
infrastructure is like five to ten years
right so basically they'd rack their
feet enough to kind of make sure that
they were not caught off guard and they
build stuff in parallel to make sure
that you know and now they're building
with AIML like all the security features
that you think about they've been like
looking at the internet and said you
know if everything's encrypted we will
start to do like ml based encryption
detection so they'll never decrypt but
they'll just say like oh you know this
type of traffic is X it behaves like
exactly traffic shaping and traffic
they'll look at traffic analysis and
look at like destinations and actually
this is why it's very important for us
to move to V6 IPv6 as well because V4
like you know there are only so many IP
addresses and if you know like the IP
address belongs to Amazon in some cases
you actually know what could be running
on top of it so if you get V6 then you
actually make this problem much more
harder because V6 has like almost
infinite addresses you know billions of
addresses and we also like we have seven
billion people so you know we need
probably like 1000 devices each and
we're coming with iot you know everyone
has so many devices at home yeah I
imagine ipv V6 is definitely I think one
of those things also that took a long
time to kind of get in and even now is
kind of still lonely slowly rolling out
right but it is still part of the IP
protocol correct so if you're moving to
UDP and you use gonna assuming that
every HTTP 3 takes off does that really
matter anymore is that IP still well I
guess IP is basically the addressing so
you it doesn't really matter you still
need you need the address yeah you need
everything you need some kind of
addressing exactly now we talked a lot
about the middle box problem the
ossification problem and the versioning
in quick and the encryption which kind
of helps solve that ossification a
little bit but what else does quick
actually have what else does http 3
bring to the table which makes it more
compelling than HTTP 2. I think Azure
like we should disambiguate the fact
that HTTP is not like HTTP 3 runs on
quick but quick is a lot more than HTTP
3. it's not just the thing that would be
on top of it
you know you could easily build an
application on top of quick which is not
HTTP right you would get a lot of like
the same benefits so you could think
about can we run webrtc see on quick for
example could we run we talk about
streaming video streaming right and
there are things like LS and dash and
like HTTP based streaming can be like do
we need HTTP now that you we have quick
can we like put media work directly do
streaming on quickly and we had this
like 25 years ago right like if anyone's
used real media player exactly that was
a proprietary right and it had rtsp and
you had like rtsp ran over to udpn you
know you had real-time streaming
protocol that was available but because
of adobe and Flash like actually people
started to use Flash video and then like
basically when Web 2.0 came and apple I
think it was mainly Apple said like you
know we will not do Adobe yeah it is
very famous flag Steve Jobs said that we
won't support that and then basically
lasted
yeah it vanished overnight so when I can
talk a little bit about the features if
you're interested in yeah it's a quick
offers so like when we had HTTP 2 there
were a lot of features that were part of
HTTP 2 which we moved into quick right
so like basically now H3 becomes like
simpler if you go back to that semantics
and syntax like semantics and syntax
becomes easier because you move a bunch
of things down so like for example the
TLs part which was really important and
you needed it for H2 was not mandated
but people wanted it moved below quick
so you don't have to worry about
encryption and such it's already
guaranteed below if you want to do
end-to-end encryption in some form you
can do it anyway on top but it's not
really needed it's like the transport is
encrypted the other thing was Zero rtt
connection so like basically if you look
at session establishment we talked about
earlier that there was like a three-way
hand change or four-way handshake yeah
and already in H2 we had like a zero rtt
but really in quick we got it for sure
basically if I've talked to you before
can we share some material from like can
I tell you that hi we talked before and
start sending you data right like that
zero RT deal so the first time you made
an unknown thing you would have to like
do all the four-way handshakes and
everything that's not but the second
time you meet you can you do it faster
do you have to do the four-way handshake
first time so assuming you have a
cryptographic key from your previous
conversation you can continue the
conversation yeah or you have like some
kind of keying material which would say
like hi and I can challenge you and say
like are you the same person and then
because there was something that was
shared before you could say like you
could answer that challenge because you
had something before correct okay so
that was one the other thing that we got
was the congestion control we talked
about this like the initial window and
we talked about this aimd which was the
very simple algorithm no one uses that
people use things like cubic and better
algorithms there's a new one that came
out from Google called bbr bottleneck
bandwidth production so
bbr basically allowed faster shaping of
traffic so you basically got that in
quick you got customized congestion
control so if you don't like this you
can build your own again you don't have
to wait for a new version of the kernel
head offline blocking we talked about
another one was migration so if you have
like if I'm on my phone and I walk into
Wi-Fi and then move to uh 4G and back I
can do connection migration without
renegotiating the session oh that's
interesting right because it's the same
zero rtt benefits idea you still have
the same connection ID and that's since
that is abstracted out of the whole UDP
stuff it doesn't oh okay that's
interesting because I think in TCP we
have the header over there right that
with the address and it's kind of tied
to your IP address so yeah and you can
just like basically say hi again right
and you just like you're like oh you
were that and then you're like okay
you're just coming from uh so is that
kind of like wouldn't that kind of
constitute from I guess a certain
perspective people being able to track
you as you move across different
networks I mean that server would anyway
be able to track you nonetheless right
like that is true yeah yeah cool yeah
even when you eventually reconnect you'd
probably be sharing some cookie or
session or something right actually you
moved it lower so like it becomes harder
for because you get this for free in
some sense like a lot of that tracking
that you were doing inside the
application there is no need for it
right so if you were doing any kind of
tracking for re-establishment or like
connection like anything in service of
like providing better service not just
for like ads and such because like in
the case of ads you definitely need it
but if you push that down like as an
application now you don't care about it
so you're not actually tracking at all
right like the thing that is tracking is
not nightclub yeah you can get you can
still provide a good service even
without having to put that ID into your
application it's part of the protocol
and because of the head of line blocking
what that means is that you have partial
reliability and you can have something
like partial reliability right so like
you can just say disconnect like I don't
want that resource so you can just say
stop on many resets on any of these
resources and earlier research was only
on a connection so like you basically if
you said you're saying goodbye but
you're not saying like I don't want this
anymore right so like basically you
could just say like I can move on to the
next resource and I can skip oh okay so
basically if you're like okay let's put
it in video terms suppose I want to I'm
streaming a video and I want to pause
this video or stop this video and then
move on to another one it doesn't mean
dropping the connection and you can just
stop that video stream yeah so within a
stream it's in order but because you
have multiple streams you can actually
basically say stop this stream get the
other stream you can re-priorize so you
get a bunch of these things and you're
right like so that's why quick is so
interesting for a lot of us because like
of course if you're building like
YouTubes and such and you're already on
HTTP too you want to use the same kind
of semantics and syntax but like now you
basically change the underpinnings
without changing the application right
so for that reason H3 is really
compelling but also compelling for other
things like web transport for example
which is its own new protocol which
basically says that I want to use quick
but I don't want to use the HTTP
semantics I want to like just you know
server initiated web transport I want to
just send data stream your data and if
you're streaming data not necessarily
video then like you need something like
a push in the old world but if you have
this and you can just open a connection
like a websocket and just say like boom
I'm gonna just send you stream data and
I'll open streams and close streams then
you can just use web transport well for
it yeah
cool that sounds really compelling so
how do you actually see this shift
happening I mean uh you probably are in
a unique position with your company and
your background to kind of see so how
much in your rough estimate would be in
the real world today how much of my
daily life is probably being run over H3
and I don't even know it probably and
YouTube and a good bit of it I imagine
Facebook YouTube I'm not on Facebook so
I can't say anymore but like there are
lots of the big Services most of the
Google properties probably already do H3
correct so the ones that save the money
like if you just think of it from a
commercial or a capitalist perspective
it's going to be YouTube for example
so on the video side is it not that
compelling would I expect Netflix or
yeah that would also be yeah but they
have plans I think like almost every
video provider has plans but they're
also thinking of media over quick
because it kind of opens a little bit
more opportunity if you think about HTTP
as like the ossification on HTTP and now
you have a quick like do you really want
to be still on top of so on on HTTP or
just create your own streaming quick and
can we like you can certainly use Quick
version one like what everyone's using
or you could have your own quick yeah
you know like in the case of Netflix it
makes sense like you have a Netflix app
more or less all of us use some kind of
app either on an Android device which is
like a Fire TV or a Chromecast or
whatever or the television itself which
is an Android box yeah you can't get
around the Netflix app because of DRM
right it's an encrypted stream anyway
and so like you said yeah they have the
client and the server on these things I
mean you can do it on the web with the
eme extension like the encrypted media
extensions like they can load the DRM
and make sure that you don't steal it
but yeah that is true like they own both
ends so it's fairly easy for them to
start innovating and I think there's a
new activity called media over quick
that started only recently like in last
year in one part of that problem is like
if you think of rtmp and I don't know
how much our listeners know about it but
it's like basically uh real-time media
protocol for you know if you have a
webcam if you have like a drone they all
have these rtmp endpoints which you know
you can stream into like that console or
wherever if you have a security camera
like all of them do rtmp and all the
live right like so a lot of these
YouTube live and such twitch like a lot
of them allow for rtmp endpoints so like
if you don't want to like use YouTube
directly to create your media you want
like you use OBS or something like that
then you can rtmp into YouTube live or
into twitch and like for example at
Daily we offer you know you you're on a
webrtc call and if you want just people
to listen to you on that webrtc call
like let's say all hands you know you
have like 10 people and you want like
100 people to or thousands of people to
watch the thing you don't want them all
on the call you can move them to rtmp
now rdmp for example is an ingest
protocol as they said so if you're a BBC
you are like you know NFL playing a game
and you want to broadcast that the
stadiums will have these rtmp cameras
just subscribe yeah we'll go to sports
center and then from SportsCenter that
would go out so the idea right now is
can we solve the ingest problem with
quick and then you get basically new
services on top of quick media over
quick with this and then you have webrtc
on the other side so basically you could
scale out to like hundreds of people or
millions of people with webrtc actually
since we've been talking about webrtc I
think it's a useful way to kind of round
out this would be to talk about webrtc
it and its rise and thing because I I
remember coming across webrtc in the
late 2000s it was like 2010 2011 2012. I
read this article now I was like wow
this is kind of a really cool thing
because at that time with doing video
call and video calls and video chats and
stuff like that was not common right it
was a tough thing to do and you had a
lot of hacky ways to get streams
together and it was unreliable and
things used to crash and browsers used
to crash and stuff like that and webrtc
came at that time I was like thinking
about this and it actually initially
came out as a peer-to-peer protocol and
I think it still is an underlying you
can technically do a peer-to-peer
connection between my browser and
somebody else's browser directly going
through peer-to-peer like this call we
are on is yeah so at that time that was
a very novel concept because and and so
I was very interested can you can you
give I mean given that your sense of
background I was just wondering maybe
you could give us a quick overview of
how it started and you know where it's
reached and where do you see this fit
into the whole internet story you're
correct that video calls have been
around since the late 80s early 90s
there was a program called WIC the main
thing to think about like the first 20
years of video calls was all about
specialized people specialized Hardware
people solve the problem and they were
specialized companies peer-to-peer
aspect was actually webrtc was not that
novel because you had Skype and some
other Technologies which were similar
which were already peer-to-peer yeah and
this kind of comes down to like you know
how the networks evolve so Napster came
out in like what 2000 1999 2000 2001
that period right and that was like
peer-to-peer music sharing right so like
but that was also kind of a proprietary
protocol it was not over HTTP I think
what webrtc brought it was already so
basically there was this peer-to-peer
stuff that was happening on one side
there was all the video stuff that was
happening on one side and web2o when it
started and Google basically brought
Chrome and said like now I have Chrome
and we have the Chrome browser which
will become the Chrome OS that already
seated that idea and then they said like
what are the services that are missing
on the Chrome browser that are available
on an operating system right and
basically device access is one and the
other one was real-time Communications
right those two things right so you did
not have access to like a Bluetooth
device or anything like you didn't have
Mouse pointers so they spun up inside
the w3c they spun up a device Group
which basically said I will find ways to
like get access to peripheral devices
that you would need access to from the
browser because the browser was actually
never allowed to have access to anything
yeah which is local right the sandbox
and could never access it could only
write right like it could only write a
file basically it's like you've
downloaded file or could just like
download it but nothing else it could
not read anything from it so like if you
think about camera and mic that's a
change in Behavior you're now reading
something right and you could always
render you had the video and the audio
tags available so you could always
render but you could not read so that
was one change and the other thing was
that as soon as you could read something
then you would say like why can't I send
my video across the internet and webrtc
was basically not a new like people talk
about it as a new protocol my opinion is
that it was a snapshot in time of the
existing protocols that existed at that
point existing and they basically said
here's a set of profiles across the
whole stack that we are mandating so
what codex right like codex h264 vp8
okay next thing RTP what flavors of RTP
what flavors of encryption over RTP RTP
being the real-time protocol that
carries the audio video right so like
basically we think of that as a pipeline
you're like oh we now have standard
interfaces in terms of API to access the
device we have standard protocol to send
the media across the internet and we
talked about Nats and firewalls and
middle boxes so you know if you're
really peer-to-peer you have to be able
to open the ports and there were already
protocols for that so like it basically
said we will use this level of X this
level of Y this level of Z
and this became the webrtc and was
really pushed by Google but then when
Google basically put the word out then
everyone was excited right like Ericsson
was excited Microsoft was excited
because they're like yeah we'll do this
and we went out and did that and I think
the first spec came out in like 2012-13
like the first draft as we call them and
personally I thought you know we would
have a big boom just like with the web
so very clearly like 1993 the web
started let's say and by 2000 was big
2012 13 webrtc started and like the idea
was that in my opinion I'm still
polishing I think it was proven
eventually that web would a webrtc would
become the dominant protocol for video
and it did like it of course took a
pandemic for all of us to like do like
100 of our traffic became like webrtc at
one point because everyone was on calls
for eight hours right so it grew
dramatically during the pandemic but it
was already really big before 2020 right
so how do you see this going uh the road
ahead right so do you see webrtc now
taking or going into quick and getting
uh taking getting getting in more and
more integrated into that side of things
yeah such a sweet right so webrtc the
sweet so like as long as you don't
change the API and like we just open
another if like just set a property in
webrtc which says like use quick then we
can just go down the pipeline and change
a bunch of things and you know to the
developer it would not matter if it's
quick or if it's pure RTP over UDP I
think the main change that we are seeing
now is what we would call unbundling of
the API because the webrtc AP is very
very opinionated like it was built for
like a certain set of use cases as you
said like it was peer-to-peer but then
we realized that for larger set of calls
the other peer can be the server and
then the server can basically so it's
back to back webrtc Connections in some
form and then you can create like you
know whatever topology you want you know
you can make a star you can make a
handlebar you know like two big servers
and like multiple fan outs on that side
or like some kind of mesh so like for
daily we have a global mesh Network
which connects everything and you will
connect to the nearest server I'll
connect to my nearest server and you
know if there are hundreds of people
they'll all connect and then we'll just
transfer media across so quick can play
a play an important role here for sure I
think the biggest thing about the
unbundling is because of machine
learning now we need to unbundle in the
middle like for example if I wanted to
voice recognition or remove the voice or
like you know background noise removal
or blur my background unless the camera
provides these Services I have to run
some kind of custom machine learning
right at the ends to be able to like do
that so there are things like the
there's like now a web codex group so
basically you would have like the device
captures codecs which are not from the
camera or from the operating system or
inside the browser you can load your own
codex or you know button score deck for
example and then you encode it and then
decode it on the other side with the
buttons decoder right right and the
codec will basically be built with the
blurring for example inside it so you
don't have to depend on a device or an
endpoint as long as you're using that
codec you know that it's going to be
blood that's that's pretty cool cool so
we spent about a good hour for this and
just wanted to kind of look back and ask
you is there something that you feel
that we have not covered that we should
cover or do you think that this is a
good overview of I think we covered
quite like you said 30 years yeah we
covered quite a lot like we covered like
three protocol families you know HTTP
UDP HTTP and webrtc and on top of that
so yeah we covered a lot of ground I
hope the listeners find some value out
of like this whole conversation I'm sure
they would I at least found a lot so you
have one person who has learned a lot so
thank you for that Warren and yeah is
there any anything that you would want
to talk about your company or I can give
you like a couple of lines about daily
so daily is a video API provider so if
you want to build like a compelling user
experience on top of video this may be
something which is just like
peer-to-peer or like
one person or a few people talking to
thousands of people you can build that
with a few lines of code and we give you
all levels of abstraction so you know no
code low code mid Code full code yeah
and the infrastructure that goes with it
so yeah we want the API to be the most
flexible API for most use cases so we
want to like cover if there's a video
use case that you have in mind and our
API cannot solve it we would love to
talk to you so like get it inside the
folder cool is there any way I mean
obviously I will be putting your
LinkedIn profile and Twitter on the show
notes is there any other way that you
would like uh listeners to I think
Twitter contact you yes or LinkedIn is
also a good place these days right okay
emails yeah I can put I can view my
email and then we can you can share that
yeah sure I'll make sure that it's in
the show notes well in that case it all
it remains is me to thank you Varun it
has been a great hour I didn't actually
even notice it an hour had passed
appreciate it so thank you for the time
and the insights and have a great day
yeah you too
[Music]
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this in all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign